Hartford Yeshiva/Hebrew Academy Collection 0007.002.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Hartford Yeshiva/Hebrew Academy
1940-2012
0007.002.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
3.0 Cubic feet 4 Boxes
The Hartford Yeshiva, founded in 1940, was the second Jewish day school established in New England. The Yeshiva was created by members of the Orthodox community who felt that only a day school could provide the quantity and quality of education needed to perpetuate traditional Judaism. At the time, the school was one of relatively few in the country that offered girls a Jewish education equal to that offered to boys. In addition to a half day of Judaic studies, the school also provided an equal amount of time on secular education and was supervised by the Hartford Board of Education. At its founding, the school immediately became a center of controversy, according to Making a Life, Building a Community, as some of the more liberal Jewish leaders in Hartford felt that such a school perpetuated the ghetto segregation left behind in Europe and was "un-American." These critics supported the use of public schools, supplemented with after school classes in Judaism, in order to promote the acculturation of the community and foster assimilation. As materials in the collection demonstrate, the Yeshiva's response to this attitude was to institute a program of patriotism to foster "Americanism." Today the school continues this practice with student charity to non-Jewish (as well as Jewish) community organizations, an annual Election Fair with local political candidates, and various patriotic programs during the year. Although most of these early critics eventually were convinced of the school's desire to fit into modern American life, some members of the community continued to feel that an Orthodox day school was a retrograde idea, even though most of the students attending the school were not "traditional" Jews. The Yeshiva, known after the early 1970s as Hebrew Academy, has responded by focusing on the quality of its secular education, establishing a computer lab, programs for the "gifted and talented" students, and active competition in statewide and national science and mathematics competitions.
Scope and Contents note
A large portion of this collection consists of materials describing various volunteer and fundraising efforts by the school, reflecting the constant need to supplement tuition
The JHSGH also has material about the Solomon Schechter Day School (West Hartford, CT) materials relating to various public schools in Hartford, such as Barnard Brown, Weaver, and Hartford Public High School, which served large Jewish populations, and materials relating to various "Talmud Torahs" in Hartford.
Americanization; Education; Hebrew Academy; Yeshiva of Hartford
- Series I: A-E
  - About this Collection, undated (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries/13th Anniversary of school ("Bar Mitzvah Anniversary"), 1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries/25th Anniversary of school, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries/40th Anniversary of school, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries/50th Anniversary of school, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Life Membership Programs, 1969?1976 (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors Given/Annual Scholarship Dinner Tribute, undated (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors Received/U.S. Dept. of Education Award, 1990?1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors/Members, undated (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors/Members/Gershman, Charles (founder), undated (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors/Planning, undated (Box 1)
  - Buildings/45 Pleasant Street, Hartford, 1942?1951 (Box 1)
  - Buildings/121 Cornwall Street, Hartford, 1951?1974 (Box 1)
  - Buildings/53 Gabb Road, Bloomfield, 1974?present, 1974-2012 (Box 1)
  - Charitable Activities, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence/Letters to parents and friends, undated (Box 1)
  - Education/Adult Programs, undated (Box 1)
  - Education/After'school Programs, undated (Box 1)
  - Education/Pre'school Programs, undated (Box 1)
  - Education/School Programs, undated (Box 1)
  - Education/School Programs/Graduations, undated (Box 1)
  - Education/Special Programs and Holiday Observances, undated
- Series II: F-Fundraising, 1948-1970
  - Financial Information, undated (Box 2)
  - Fundraising/Ad Journals, undated (Box 2)
  - Fundraising/Ad Journals ("Yearbook"), 1948-1970 (Box 2)
- Series III: Fundraising, 1975-2000s
  - Fundraising/Ad Journals ("Yearbook;" or "Scholarship Dinner"), 1971-2000s, 1971-2012 (Box 3)
- Series IV: Fundraising/endowments -Z
  - Fundraising/Endowments and Grants, undated (Box 4)
  - Fundraising/Planning, undated (Box 4)
  - Fundraising/Projects A?D, undated (Box 4)
  - Fundraising/Projects E?Z, undated (Box 4)
  - Fundraising/Student Fundraising Projects, undated (Box 4)
  - Historical Highlights, undated (Box 4)
  - Interfaith Activities, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/"Chadashot", undated (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/"Hakesher", undated (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/"H.A. Link", undated (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/"Menu" (weekly news for parents), undated (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/"The Advocate" "Update", undated (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 4)
  - Open Houses and Recruitment, undated (Box 4)
  - Parent Handbook, undated (Box 4)
  - Publicity/Promotional Materials, undated (Box 4)
  - Publicity/Promotional Materials/Calendars, 1997- (Box 4)
  - Social Events/Annual Purim Dinner, etc., undated (Box 4)
  - Social Events/Miscellaneous/ and Special, undated (Box 4)
  - Staff Members, undated (Box 4)
  - Volunteers/Fathers' Club, undated (Box 4)
  - Volunteers/P.T.A., undated (Box 4)
  - Volunteers/Women's Organization, undated (Box 4)
- Photographs:
  - See: "Photographs/Education/Hartford Yeshiva?Hebrew Academy", undated
- Oral Histories:
  - Gershman Memorial Convocation, Tape #213 (1980)
- Scrapbooks
- Artifacts:
  - Hat and two badges from "Israel at 50" program, 1998
  - Trowel from cornerstone laying given to Herman Eisenberg, April 18, 1950
- Oversized Materials